Works Progress Administration (WPA) Phonodisc Collection
Works Progress Administration (WPA) Phonodisc Collection
1936-1942
Federal Music Project
351 items
Collection of recordings from the United States Work Projects Administration's Federal Music Project
5481395
Biographical History
The Federal Music Project (FMP) was one of five arts-related programs sponsored by the Work Projects Administration (WPA) during the Great Depression. The other four were the Federal Art Project, Federal Theatre Project, Federal Writers' Project, and Historical Records Survey.
The FMP was established in 1935 and Russian-American violinist Dr. Nikolai Sokoloff appointed its head; American musicologist, composer, teacher, and folklorist Charles Seeger (father of folk singer Pete Seeger) was later brought on board as assistant director. The program sponsored musical performances, classes, concerts, and ethnomusicology work around the country. Its primary goal was employment of out-of-work musicians, conductors and composers; its secondary goals were to encourage music appreciation and instruction, copy and distribute music, document musical activity (including folk songs) in the United States, and provide affordable entertainment for poor families and encourage the musical arts. It also distrubuted thousands of recordings to radio stations around the country.
The project was highly successful, particularly in encouraging music classes in public schools. The FMP's funding was drastically reduced in 1939 (at this time it was also renamed the WPA Music Program) and phased out entirely by the middle of World War II.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Works Progress Administration (WPA) Phonodisc Collection contains more than 350 recordings created a under the auspices of the Federal Music Project and distributed to hundreds of radio stations around the United States. The format, known as electrical transcription discs, was exclusively for radio stations and is of a higher sound quality than standard LPs.
Recordings cover a range of vocal and instrumental styles and genres, including classical music, popular music, spirituals, madrigals, choral works, opera and American folk songs. Groups represented include orchestras, military bands, dance bands, professional choruses, children's choirs, and African-American groups. The majority of performers hailed from Boston, New York, or California; the latter include several whose focus was Mexican music. Some of the discs include a guest speaker or a WPA "spot" advertising the project.
Arrangement of the Collection
Discs are shelved individually, in order by season and program number. To request an item, please provide year, program number, title and ID number (e.g. "1936, Program No. 35 Works Progress Administration Presents The Manhattan Concert Band, wpa_phono_035").
Related Material
See also the
Federal Theater Project Collection
. also has the papers of several artists who were part of the Federal Art Project; please to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; Politics, government and public administration; Radio, television, film; American Folk Singers of Boston.; Federal Music Project (U.S.); Los Angeles Mexican Chorus.; Los Angeles Mexican Orchestra.; Negro Melody Singers.; Southern California Mexican Tipica Orchestra.; United States Army Band.; United States Navy Band.; United States. -- Work Projects Administration.; United States. -- Works Progress Administration.; African American choirs.; Children's choirs.; Folk music -- Mexico.; Folk music -- United States.; Madrigals.; Music.; Opera.; Symphony orchestras -- United States.; Long-playing records.; Sound recordings.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from the Newberry Library, Chicago, 2019.
Inventory
- 1936 season
  Discs are shelved individually. To request an item, please provide year, program number, title and ID number (e.g. "1936, Program No. 35 Works Progress Administration Presents The Manhattan Concert Band, wpa_phono_035")
  - Program No. 1 Works Progress Administration Presents New York State Symphonic Band, 1936; wpa_phono_001; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Dance of the hours; Alla turca; WPA spot
  - Program No. 2 Works Progress Administration Presents The Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_002; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    March to the Tournament; The Canzonetta; WPA spot; Overture to Stradella
  - Program No. 3 Works Progress Administration Presents Municipal Dance Band, 1936; wpa_phono_003; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Tormented; Rigamarole; WPA spot; The touch of your lips; Harlem heat
  - Program No. 4 Works Progress Administration Presents Negro Melody Singers, 1936; wpa_phono_004; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Roll, Jordan, roll; Short'nin' bread; Were you there when they crucified my Lord?; WPA spot; Ezekiel saw the wheel; Gospel train; Same train; Swing low, sweet chariot (excerpt)
  - Program No. 5 Works Progress Administration Presents Children's Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_005; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    This program features music performed by a children's orchestra, age 8 and 16. None of the children had ever played a musical instrument before. They were trained by Vincenzo Palladino and play on mandolin, mandola, guitar and bass. Serenata; Two guitars; WPA spot; Andante and Tempo di polka; Ibanez, arranger
  - Program No. 6 Works Progress Administration Presents New York Civic Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_006; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Allegretto from Brahms' 2nd symphony; WPA spot; Finlandia
  - Program No. 7 Works Progress Administration Presents The Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_007; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    March from Tannhäuser; WPA spot; Babillage; Overture to Norma
  - Program No. 8 Works Progress Administration Presents Negro Art Singers, 1936; wpa_phono_008; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00 (Oversize 1)
    Go down, oh sun, in blood; A loving heart; Immortal Zeus; Didn't my Lord deliver Daniel?, arranged for double quartet, unaccompanied; Wade in the water, soloists with double quartet, unaccompanied; WPA spot; Swing along, chorus with piano accompaniment.
  - Program No. 9 Works Progress Administration Presents Municipal Dance Band, 1936; wpa_phono_009; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Say it with music; I'm putting all my eggs in one basket; Please believe me; WPA spot; The day I let you get away; Cling to me; Let yourself go
  - Program No. 10 Works Progress Administration Presents New York Festival Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_010; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Overture to Phèdre; WPA spot; Der Rosenkavalier waltz
  - Program No. 11 Works Progress Administration Presents New York Festival Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_011; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Entr'acte and ballet from Act 3 of Raymonda; Ballet of the Sylphes; WPA spot; Three Hungarian dances
  - Program No. 12 Works Progress Administration Presents The Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_012; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Coronation march from La Prophète; Selections from Naughty Marietta; WPA spot; Stars and stripes forever
  - Program No. 13 Works Progress Administration Presents Negro Melody Singers, 1936; wpa_phono_013; unaccompanied chorus and soloist performances of spiritual music; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Free at last; Who'll join that union; Who built the ark?; WPA spot; Certainly Lord; Dis train; Same train; Sign of the judgment.
  - Program No. 14 Works Progress Administration Presents The Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_014; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Our favorite regiment march; Pas des fleurs from the ballet Naila; WPA spot; Selections from the operetta Rose Marie
  - Program No. 15 Works Progress Administration Presents Children's Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_015; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    This program features music performed by a children's orchestra, age 8 and 16. Non of the children had ever played a musical instrument before. They were trained by Vincenzo Palladino and play on mandolin, mandola, guitar and bass. Serenade; Carnival in Venice; WPA spot; Children's march
  - Program No. 16 Works Progress Administration Presents Negro Melody Singers, 1936; wpa_phono_016; folk songs and spirituals, by unaccompanied chorus and soloists; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Carry me back to old Virginny; Live-a humble; Joe Brown's coal mine; WPA spot re: School Lunch Program; Street vendor cries from various cities: Boston, New York City, Philadelphia, North Carolina, Charleston S.C.); In dat great gittin' up mornin'
  - Program No. 17 Works Progress Administration Presents Negro Melody Singers, 1936; wpa_phono_017; unaccompanied chorus and soloist performances of spiritual music; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Where shall I be when the first trumpet sounds; Great day the righteous marches; Joshua fit the battle of Jericho; WPA spot; Tell me, who do you call the wonderful counselor; I've been in the storm so long; Oh, my lovin' brother
  - Program No. 18 Works Progress Administration Presents Schubert Group, 1936; wpa_phono_018; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Nocturne in F sharp; The mermaid song; WPA spot; La Gitana; Two grenadiers; Joseph Posner, baritone; Madame Annette Royak, soprano, Berta Vandenberg [?]
  - Program No. 19 Works Progress Administration Presents the Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_019; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    The thunderer; WPA spot; Le Feria, Suite espagnole. Los Toros; Serenade la reja; La zarzuela
  - Program No. 20 Works Progress Administration Presents Composers' Forum-Laboratory, 1936; wpa_phono_020; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    The valley of the muted songbirds; Scherzo from the South; Cradle song; WPA spot; Hotel music, 2nd movement: Turkey trot; Grand valse de concert; Reverie, Andre Skalski [?], piano; Abe Veder [?], cello
  - Program No. 21 Works Progress Administration Presents the Knickerbocker Little Symphony, 1936; wpa_phono_021; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Morning and Anitra's dance from Peer Gynt Suite; WPA spot; Artist's life waltz
  - Program No. 22 Works Progress Administration Presents Artist Recital Bureau, 1936; wpa_phono_022; vocal soloists with piano accompaniment and a violin performance; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Give a man a horse he can ride; Blow, blow, thou winter wind; Danse espagnole; WPA spot; The star; I love life
  - Program No. 23 Works Progress Administration Presents the Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_023; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Egyptian ballet. Allegro; Allegretto Scherzando; WPA spot; Egyptian ballet. Andante; Allegro non troppo
  - Program No. 24 Works Progress Administration Presents Artist Recital Bureau, 1936; wpa_phono_024; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Vocal and violin soloists with piano accompaniments. Sweet thoughts of home; Bagatelle; WPA spot; None but the lonely heart; A vucchella; Life
  - Program No. 25 Works Progress Administration Presents Municipal Dance Band, 1936; wpa_phono_025; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Wahoo; Let's face the music and dance; Yours truly is truly yours; WPA spot; But where are you; You hit the spot; Say it with music
  - Program No. 26 Works Progress Administration Presents the Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_026; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Nibelungen march; WPA spot; Loin du Ball; Flight of the bumble bee; Selections from Fortune teller
  - Program No. 27 Works Progress Administration Presents New York Civic Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_027; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Prelude to Lohengrin; WPA spot; Dance of the buffoons from The Snow Maiden
  - Program No. 28 Works Progress Administration Presents Negro Art Singers, 1936; wpa_phono_028; spirituals, by soloists and chorus with and without piano accompaniment; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    If you love god, serve him; King Emanuel; WPA spot; There's going to be a land slide; That great getting up morning
  - Program No. 29 Works Progress Administration Presents the Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_029; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Semper fidelis march; Waltz Dream; WPA spot; Selections from the chimes of Normandy
  - Program No. 30 Works Progress Administration Presents Artist Recital Bureau, 1936; wpa_phono_030; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Ah, love but a day, William Reed, pianist; Return; La capricieuse Op. 17, Berte Vandenberg [?], pianist; WPA spot; I heard you go by; Thou art so like a flower, Berte Vandenberg [?], pianist
  - Program No. 31 Works Progress Administration Presents Municipal Dance Band, 1936; wpa_phono_031; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Is it true what they say about Dixie; Lost; La cucaracha; WPA spot; Lights out; High rhythm and low moaning
  - Program No. 32 Works Progress Administration Presents Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_032; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Second L'Arlesienne suite; WPA spot; Three dances from Henry VIII suite: Morris dance; Shepherd's dance; Torch dance
  - Program No. 33 Works Progress Administration Presents Municipal Dance Band, 1936; wpa_phono_033; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Swing, Mr. Charlie; Melody from out of the sky, from 1936 film "Trail of the Lonesome Pine"; Waltz tune: It's a sin to tell a lie; WPA spot; What's the name of that song; Goody Goody.
  - Program No. 34 Works Progress Administration Presents The Knickerbocker [Little] Symphony, 1936; wpa_phono_034; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Andante from Ukrainian suite, 5th movement; WPA spot; Tales from the Vienna Woods - waltz
  - Program No. 35 Works Progress Administration Presents The Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_035; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    March of the gladiator; La cinquantaine; WPA spot; Fifth Hungarian dance; Sixth Hungarian dance.
  - Program No. 36 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Dance Band, 1936; wpa_phono_036; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Memories of a dying savage; Smoke gets in your eyes; WPA spot; Goody goody, uncredited female vocalist; Dancing dogs
  - Program No. 37 Works Progress Administration Presents New York Civic Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_037; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    The enchanted lake; WPA spot; Valse caprice
  - Program No. 38 Works Progress Administration Presents New York State Symphonic Band, 1936; wpa_phono_038; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Overture to William Tell; WPA spot; Minute waltz
  - Program No. 39 Works Progress Administration Presents The Knickerbocker [Little] Symphony, 1936; wpa_phono_039; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Symphony no. 1 in C major. Andante con moto; WPA spot; Trepak from the Nutcracker suite; Slavonic dance
  - Program No. 40 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Dance Band, 1936; wpa_phono_040; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Somebody stole my girl, uncredited male vocalist with refrain in Ted Lewis style; Lights out, uncredited male and female duet; WPA spot; Play, fiddle play; Is she my baby, well, I'll say, unpublished tune.
  - Program No. 41 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Dance Band, 1936; wpa_phono_041; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Melody from the sky, from the film Trail of the Lonesome Pine, uncredited male vocalist; Moonlight Madonna; WPA spot; Sylvia; Rockin' in Rhythm
  - Program No. 42 Works Progress Administration Presents New York State Symphonic Band, 1936; wpa_phono_042; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00 (Oversize 1)
    Grand triumphal march from Aida; WPA spot; Suite of contrast. Love song; Festive dance - Bacchante; Nearer my God to Thee
  - Program No. 43 Works Progress Administration Presents Brooklyn Symphony, 1936; wpa_phono_043; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Second Peer Gynt suite. Ingrid's lament; WPA spot; Second L'Arlesienne suite. Intermezzo; Farandole
  - Program No. 44 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Symphony Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_044; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Minuet; WPA spot; Introduction to The Bird of Paradise; Forgotten Island; African Dance, from 1933 film "King Kong".
  - Program No. 45 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Dance Band, 1936; wpa_phono_045; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Lost, uncredited vocal duet; The words are in my heart, from the 1935 film "Gold Diggers"; WPA spot; Alone, from 1935 film "A Night at the Opera"; Stompin' Around.
  - Program No. 46 Works Progress Administration Presents The Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_046; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Woodland Whispers; Thunder and blazes; WPA spot; Serenade Badine
  - Program No. 47 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Dance Band, 1936; wpa_phono_047; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    You, from 1936 film "The Great Ziegfeld"; Moon melody, rumba; WPA spot; Tell me that you love me tonight, waltz song with uncredited vocal duet; I'm gonna sit right down and write myself a letter; uncredited female vocalist.
  - Program No. 48 Works Progress Administration Presents The Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_048; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    March Militaire; WPA spot; Wine, Women, and Song
  - Program No. 49 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Symphony Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_049; Grooved analog disc; running time 14:45
    Carnival overture, Op. 92; WPA spot; Intermezzo from Carmen; Hungarian Dance in G minor, flute and harp with orchestral obbligato.
  - Program No. 50 Works Progress Administration Presents Brooklyn Symphony, 1936; wpa_phono_050; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Overture to The Barber of Seville, commentary by announcer on the history of the piece; WPA spot; Apprentices' Dance, Entrance of the Meistersinger, Act 3, from Die Meistersinger
  - Program No. 51 Works Progress Administration Presents New York State Symphonic Band, 1936; wpa_phono_051; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Overture to La Forza del Destino; WPA spot; Love's Dream after the Ball, Op. 356, waltz
  - Program No. 52 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Negro Choir, 1936; wpa_phono_052; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    I couldn't hear nobody pray, sung by soloist Bernice Ellis Rundall [?]; Dark Water; WPA spot; Little David, sung by soloists D. A. Scott and William Stocks [?]; Swanee River; In that Great Gettin' Up Mornin', uncredited piano accompanist.
  - Program No. 53 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Symphony Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_053; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Wolf dance from the Thunderbird suite, based on a Blackfoot Indian dance; WPA spot; Danse Macabre; Hungarian Dance no. 5
  - Program No. 54 Works Progress Administration Presents Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_054; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Second Suite in F major, Op. 28 - March, composed of 3 English folk dances: Morris Dance; Swansea Town; Cloudy Banks; Song without words: I'll love my love; Song of the blacksmith; Fantasia on Dargason; WPA spot; Washington Post March.
  - Program No. 55 Works Progress Administration Presents Artist Recital Bureau, 1936; wpa_phono_055; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    The last hour, William Reed, piano; A minor Mazurka, Berta Vandenberg [?] piano; Frasquita serenade; WPA spot; Tell me, oh blue, blue sky; Do you know my garden?
  - Program No. 56 Works Progress Administration Presents the Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_056; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Our flirtations; You and you, waltz from Die Fledermaus; WPA spot; Au Moulin, referred to as In the Mill
  - Program No. 57 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles [A] Capella Choir, 1936; wpa_phono_057; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Choir of 50 voices. Nightingale, sung by soloist Robert Cohn [?]; Under the Greenwood Tree; WPA spot; Dainty, Fine, Sweet Nymph; The Australian Up Country Song, wordless Australian bushman's song.
  - Program No. 58 Works Progress Administration Presents New York Civic Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_058; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Overture to Sicilian Vespers; WPA spot; Dance of the Nymphs and Dryads
  - Program No. 59 Works Progress Administration Presents New York State Symphonic Band, 1936; wpa_phono_059; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Fantasy, Way down south. Dixie; Swanee River; Carry me back to ol' Virginny; WPA spot; Spanish dance, Moraima
  - Program No. 60 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Symphony Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_060; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Plantation dances; Merry-go-round, from At the Fair suite; WPA spot; Allegro con Brio, 3rd movement from Romantic Symphony
  - Program No. 61 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Folk Lore Choir, 1936; wpa_phono_061; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Ack Värmeland Du sköna, sung in Swedish, Victor Rockwood, soloist; Museimein [?], sung in Italian, chorus with piano; Litania di Maria, religious song, choir with piano; WPA spot; In Derry Down Dale, Victor Rockwood, soloist with piano accompaniment; Prison Song, sung in Russian, chorus with piano; Venetian Bacaro, sung in Italian, chorus with piano.
  - Program No. 62 Works Progress Administration Presents Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_062; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    March Bombasto; Humoresque; WPA spot; Bacchanale from Samson and Delilah
  - Program No. 63 Works Progress Administration Presents [the] Knickerbocker Little Symphony, 1936; wpa_phono_063; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Overture to Die Fledermaus; WPA spot; Dance from Neapolitan scenes (Tarantella)
  - Program No. 64 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Negro Choir, 1936; wpa_phono_064; soloists and chorus of 50 voices; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Cert'n'y Lord, sung by soloist Edna Herb [?]; I gotta home in that rock, sung by soloist William Storks [?]; WPA spot; Go Down, Moses, sung by soloist Gonzolo James [?]; Be ready when he comes, chorus; Four and twenty elders, sung by soloist D. A. Scott [?]; Good News, sung by soloist Forest Prince [?].
  - Program No. 65 Works Progress Administration Presents Brooklyn Symphony, 1936; wpa_phono_065; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Intermezzo from Cavalleria Rusticana; Prelude to 4th act of La Traviata; WPA spot; March from Tannhauser
  - Program No. 66 Works Progress Administration Presents [the] Manhattan Concert Band, 1936; wpa_phono_066; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Belle of Chicago; Valse Triste, Op. 44, No. 1; WPA spot; Fete Boheme from Scenes Pittoresques
  - Program No. 67 Works Progress Administration Presents New York Civic Orchestra, 1936; wpa_phono_067; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00
    Prelude to Die Lorelei; WPA spot; In War-Time, 3rd movement from Indian Suite
  - Program No. 68 Works Progress Administration Presents Los Angeles Folk Lore Choir, 1936; wpa_phono_068; folk songs, performed by chorus and various soloists with piano accompaniment.; Grooved analog disc; running time 15:00